Well, nobody can work correctly.
Are you OK?
So, this is the basis...
the basis of our intentions.
To explain to you in this debate, the meaning
of their commitment within the Front De Gauche...
Oh there's the star!
I think we can't speak here !
So, the canditates to the Socialists presidential primaries
for reasons we understand,
say : "we have to go to the F̻te de l'Huma,
and approach the Front De Gauche."
So to us it means - and that's a good news -
that the time for contempt is over,
and that they'll start to say
what they think about what's in there.
That is what matters, not me.
Are you OK?
Thank you for your invitation.
The one who will lead will be supported by the others.
I think, that if I'm leading the Left,
as the Socialist party's prime secretary just told you,
they will vote for me. Done !
Harlem Desir : And Vice Versa!