Hello and welcome to this new edition of the Schkopi Show.
We have exciting things in store for you today,
first an interview with harmonicist Frédéric Yonnet,
then a fan interview like no other with Olimpia.
Next, our princely experts will exchange their opinions
about Prince as a composer and producer.
Finally, we'll end this show with an improvised jam session
with Dom Briki and Frédéric Yonnet.
Let's go for the 3rd Schkopi Show !
We're fortunate to have harmonicist Frédéric Yonnet for our show.
Welcome and thank you, Frédéric, for accepting our invitation.
For those who don't know you, you're a world renowned artist.
You had the opportunity to play with great artists in France, Europe,
Africa and the United States.
That said, could you present us in a few words your career path ?
My career path ?
As you said I'm Frédéric Yonnet, I'm a Frenchman living in the United-States
and I play the diatonic harmonica.
I moved to the United States almost 10 years ago.
When I was still in Paris, I worked at the Canal + TV channel
with people like Patrick Ferbac and Lol et le Groupe.
I also recorded for Guesch Patti, Blue Fever and many others ...
How did you start playing the harmonica ? When did you get that passion for it ?
My passion for it came naturally.
It's an attractive instrument in itself.
It fits in your pocket and it isn't very expensive.
Moreover, there's a whole range of sounds that can come out of this instrument,
which is actually very little known and highly stereotyped as belonging to blues
or country music.
I actually realized there was a huge potential in a music genre in which
I identified myself more.
It's true that it's an instrument somewhat underestimated
and which isn't as easy to handle as it seems.
Most of the time the audience respects more guitarists
such as Carlos Santana, Jimi Hendrix, Keith Richards and Prince of course.
But who were your inspirations ?
Who were the people who influenced you to keep playing ?
I was influenced by some of the most renowned harmonicists,
such as Stevie Wonder of course,
then there is in the jazz world the absolutely phenomenal Toots Thielemans
who is from Brussels.
But, these harmonicists play a different instrument,
since they play the chromatic harmonica.
And I finally realized in the world of the diatonic harmonica,
there were very few people who had incorporated the instrument
into a bit more elaborated music than blues or country.
For example, in jazz and fusion music,
there are almost only Howard Levy or maybe French harmonicist
Sébastien Charlier.
They really work to integrate the harmonica into a bit more elaborated music.
So I thought there was an opportunity for me.
What you just said enables me to talk about what I read on your website.
I quote: "Frédéric Yonnet's ability to play chromatic scales
on the diatonic harmonica surprises people !
It enables him to have a wide range of sounds,
of which he can use every possibility.
Everyone is amazed by his technical mastery of the 12 keys.
Lovers of 2 harmonicas, chromatic and diatonic, applaud him !"
So, for people like me who aren't at all musicians,
could you explain to us what's the difference between a chromatic harmonica
and a diatonic one ?
I'm gonna make it easy for everybody to understand.
It's great there's a microphone on the table because we can take advantage of it.
The diatonic harmonica is an instrument which only has 19 notes over 3 octaves.
So, a harmonica in C has the C,D,E,F,G,A,B,C notes.
Although, not all the harmonica notes are here,
in some sides of the harmonica they have to be created artificially.
So, actually, a harmonica in C gives you these sounds -
That's what you get from a harmonica in C.
These are all the notes on this harmonica,
although half of them are really artificial, but let's move on.
On a chromatic harmonica, in fact, there are 2 harmonicas
combined on the same instrument.
That is to say, there are one instrument in C and an instrument tuned
a semitone above in C-sharp.
As a result, it enables to access to all the black and white keys
on the piano keyboard.
That is to say, you get this -
Ok ?
Ok, I got it.
What I do with my instrument, in fact, is that I combine the 2 instruments
into 1 only harmonica.
This means that roughly 45% of the notes I play do not exist
naturally on the instrument,
but I created them artificially in order to have a chromatic range
which includes the C scale and the C sharp one.
Ok, it's much more clear now.
Now, I understand why people consider you a true harmonica virtuoso.
And you started your career at only 19 with, what you previously mentioned,
appearances on the Nulle Part Ailleurs TV show.
Congratulations for having started a career at 19, tell me what's your secret ?!
Lots of work !
I guess.
Lots of work and perseverance.
I went out a lot in jazz clubs and did jam sessions.
I also worked a lot with musicians who had the patience to explain
what they expected from me
and pushed me into a corner of an instrument which is theoretically limited.
I think what really helped me to move forward pretty quickly,
was to understand the limits of the instrument
didn't really exist in the instrument, but more in myself.
So when I started to broaden a little bit my vision of the instrument
and music and to learn things,
I managed to incorporate them into my way of playing.
And as soon as you launched your career,
you decided right away to go to the United States.
Nobody knew you or expected you, but anyway you decided to go there.
The fact that nobody knew me or expected me helped me.
Let's go back to your beginnings in the USA.
You were only 19 ... well, maybe a little bit older.
Indeed, I was a little bit older, I was 24 when I left.
It was still a young age to do this.
Thank you.
In fact, I left around 24/25.
When I arrived there, I started a little to connect to the jazz scene
of Washington D.C, where there are a lot of musicians.
There is a huge jazz culture over there.
Duke Ellington was born in Washington D.C.
So, local musicians are proud to make it their duty to maintain
the jazz swing culture which Duke Ellington developed.
And alongside that, there is a more underground scene called the go-go,
which is actually a kind of funk with heavy African accents.
There's a lot of percussion in go-go music, which makes it very captivating.
Usually when you go to a go-go concert, it starts around midnight/1 o'clock AM
and musicians play till all hours.
They never stop because they play songs one after another
that are based on the same rhythm, which is kind of a jerky one.
I hope we can find music examples of this, I don't want to offend
go-go musicians by imitating them, because if I do,
I'm going to be stoned to death when I go back to ashington D.C.
No, no, don't worry, they don't watch us in Washington D.C.
We won't subtitle this part of the show.
Thanks.
I'd like to go back to your first 2 albums.
If I'm not wrong, first, there is Blowing Your Mind in Every Key of the Harp !
I had a hard time remembering it.
You're not wrong, I'm impressed !
And the second is called Front & Center.
Great !
I have a good memory, I did my homework a little bit before coming.
How was the recording process during these 2 albums ?
Do you have stories to share or collaborations that you did
and want to talk about ?
When I started working on Blowing Your Mind ..., it was meant to be a demo.
I tried to do a 5-track demo, in order to get gigs in Washington D.C
and to become known.
At the end of my first few gigs, people came to ask me to buy the demo,
so we decided to pack it, make a record sleeve and put a cover photo.
A few thousand units were sold, which wasn't bad for a demo.
It was my 5-track first album.
Then, I decided to develop all that on a full-length album, so Front & Center.
It was at the time when it was still considered innovative
to create music on a computer.
I'm even tempted to call it computer music.
It was the transition from tape to hard disk.
I took the opportunity at that time to make half the group in France play,
and then to go back in the US with the tapes and to make them be played
with American musicians.
So, it was a real international project.
I have a Madagascan guitarist who lives in Paris.
I have a French percussionist called Patrick Ferbac,
who is now the artistic director of artist Grand Corps Malade,
and whom I met on Nulle Part Ailleurs.
And then all the rest of the musicians are in Washington D.C.
I managed to combine all that and yet these people have never met.
This is one of the stories I can share.
And it seems you're at the forefront of technology with your last output
Reed My Lips.
I'll remind people of the concept for those who haven't watched
the 1st Schkopi Show, which is very bad.
It's a reality CD concept.
For now, you can buy this card which gives you access to
the demo version of the album
and you can provide feedback that will be taken into account for its final version.
How did you get that idea ?
Is it because the music industry is in a bad state ?
Because the traditional way of making music
no longer matches market expectations ?
There were 2 things.
On the one hand, the truth is that people began to revive me
on the evolution of my 3rd project.
And my musical career over the last 4 years really pushed me to meet people
who could have an enormous influence on my project.
So I started to be more careful about the way I was moving on
by inviting people to participate in the album.
And their schedule began to affect mine.
Finally, I decided to anticipate on the usual album idea and distribute its rough cut,
and at the same time I took the opportunity to plant a seed of creativity
in the minds of people who can listen to the album.
The other thing that happened was that I had this idea exactly a year
after I started working with Prince.
And working with him opened my eyes on the music industry.
We all know that record companies are wasting away.
But working with him opened my eyes to the fact
it actually turns into a world of opportunities for independent artists
rather than being a big calamity that is falling down upon us.
So I started to change a little bit my perception of the music industry.
And I thought why not enjoy it and invite people to participate in a reality CD ?
Have you already received some feedback?
Have you already begun to work again
on the album following all the advice given ?
Yes, and I'm sorry if I haven't yet put the new songs on the server,
but I'll do it when I get back to Washington D.C.
I have already completed a new version of the album.
I got very positive feedback.
People are very excited about it because they actually feel like
they're part of the project,
and so it belongs to them a little bit too, which is a very good thing.
Maybe this project will help you to promote an harmonica-oriented album,
because I guess this isn't an easy task.
Of course, one can think of Stevie Wonder who had used a pseudonym
when he launched his harmonica-oriented album.
So how do you manage to promote such an unusual project ?
It's a good way to describe it.
Let's say that in what I do, I consider that my mission is accomplished
when I succeed in broadening people's perception of the harmonica,
that is to say when I get to break a little bit the stereotypes attached to it
such as its use only in blues, country or rock music.
And so this concept is a little bit in the same vein, it goes in the same direction.
In the versions currently available on the website, you mainly play the harmonica,
but do you play any other instruments or do you rely on other people ?
No, I wouldn't like to offend the people who listen to my album,
because most people who are into this kind of music would hear the difference
since they are musicians themselves, or at least music lovers.
They would soon realize this isn't a real drummer or a real bass player
on the recording.
Don't underestimate yourself !
No, I prefer to work on what I do best and leave what's left to do to my musicians
who are absolutely extraordinary, for whom I have great respect
and who inspire me.
That's actually the purpose of a project like this one,
because if I did everything all alone,
it would soon begin to be a very self-absorbed project.
And what I really want to do is to include as many people as possible
in this project
whether they are artists or fans.
All the musicians are from Washington D.C and Paris.
I used the same approach as before with the great help of the Internet.
It made it easier to achieve.
Exactly.
So, Patrick Ferbac once again did percussion on it
and I have other French friends who will participate in it.
No, it's important that everything doesn't come from me,
I think it would be a shame if it did.
In fact, it was a collective project.
Exactly.
As I mentioned earlier you're a world renowned artist,
and you just came back from Beirut.
What were you doing there ?
I was in Beirut to play with a new trio which has just been set up,
and that includes Patrick Ferbac and the Buddha Bar DJ  DJ Ravin.
We are a trio, the DJ as turntablist, Patrick plays percussion
and I play the harmonica.
We do electro-lounge music, now more jazz-oriented,
since live instruments are played.
We will start to tour a bit more with this trio,
it's a very interesting project and I'm very happy to be part of it.
I would like to talk about your collaborations.
You already mentioned Grand Corps Malade,
and we also know you worked with Eryka Badu and John Legend.
How did these meetings go ?
What projects did you do together ?
With Eryka, it's a family affair if I may say.
We know very well each other and we get along really well
and we spend a lot of time privately.
We spend more time together in our private lives than in our professional lives.
I did concerts and tours with her.
We spent a lot of time doing music, but there aren't any recordings yet,
so that's what I'm trying to do with her now.
Ok, so it's planned.
Absolutely.
With John Legend, well, it was extraordinary.
He organized a fundraiser in Philadelphia,
and he invited me to participate in his concert.
I believe it was captured on film, there is a video somewhere online,
I'll try to find it.
We'll get it. Who else did you mention ?
Grand Corps Malade.
It was a very very emotional moment with him,
because my parents hit the road and went to Normandy to attend the 2 concerts.
And I think they were the last concerts
I did that my mother had the opportunity to attend before she passed away.
I understand.
On your Facebook profile, I saw you posed for pictures with other stars
including Chuck Brown and Quincy Jones.
Do you have projects with them?
What happened ? What these meetings were about ?
Chuck Brown and I are both part of the Washington D.C music community,
so we pass each other a lot, and also we share the same musicians.
A trombonist like Greg Boyer, who was on tour with Prince,
tours continuously with Chuck Brown.
The same goes for Quincy Jones, he's an extraordinary character.
There are a tremendous passion and generosity through what he does,
but he is very very busy in the music industry, so it's hard to get him.
And every time we spend time together,
we try to solve the world's problems, have drinks and speak French,
but there's still no music project planned, that said we're working on it.
Now I'd like to talk about the ultra mega superstars with whom you worked with,
such as Stevie Wonder, of course.
So I guess that as an harmonicist it was something huge to work
with Stevie Wonder.
You must tell us juicy stories about this collaboration.
Juicy stories about this collaboration ...
Or not that juicy.
I'll tell you the juiciest part after the video cameras are turned off.
I think that's a pretty good story to share to tell you how I met Stevie.
I met him in Los Angeles at the 2006 Grammy Awards.
A friend of mine, Dave Chappelle, was set to introduce
Sly & the Family Stone at the Grammy Awards, they were making a comeback.
It was quite an interesting performance,
I hope you'll get a chance to find it on YouTube because lots of things happened.
We'll watch it.
Go and see it on the net because it's quite interesting what happened.
That said, I was backstage with Dave,
and we were walking around a little in the corridor.
It was like I was walking around in a record store
and all the records were walking alive before me,
like Sting or Madonna.
Indeed, that must be something huge !
Yes, it was really magical.
And then, a moment later, we walked past a closed door
and I saw Stevie Wonder's name written on it.
Obviously, I started to lose my cool and I asked Dave
if he could introduce me to Stevie,
which he did with no problem at all.
He introduced me to Stevie and explained to him I was a French harmonicist.
As usual, Stevie was really kind and generous.
He shook my hand and told me, "Wow ! Nice to meet you etc ..."
And then, something interesting happened.
The attention on Stevie began to fade
and the people who introduced us began to talk among themselves.
So I found myself in Los Angeles at the Grammys alone with Stevie.
And since everyone left us literally alone I took the opportunity to ask him
what harmonica brand he was using.
He said he was using Hohner.
And I asked if he ever heard of the Zidle brand.
He said no and asked me if it was a good one.
And I told him to just let me show him to judge its quality.
So I pulled out of my pocket my harmonica and played him one of his songs.
During the whole thing, he had his hand on my arm like this.
He was listening to me and after a while he began to do this.
I finished the song and asked him if it reminded him of something.
He said, Of course ! and asked me if it was a chromatic harmonica.
In my opinion, this was the greatest compliment he could give me
because Stevie has been playing the chromatic harmonica since his youth.
So he couldn't tell the difference between the blues harmonica
and the instrument he plays,
because I succeeded in playing scales he has access with his instrument
on an instrument which doesn't have them naturally.
So later in our relationship, I had the opportunity to explain to him
the technique I apply on the diatonic instrument,
and he has well progressed since.
You give lessons to Stevie Wonder.
I just want to point it out to the people who are watching us.
This is the man who gives lessons to Stevie Wonder, he's not just anyone.
I don't know if one can put it this way.
Let's just say I showed him a trick.
Is there a collaboration planned ?
We plan to work together.
Can you tell us a bit more about it ?
I don't want to sound superstitious but I'd rather keep it to myself,
so when it comes out it will have more impact,
because I believe from all the projects I have,
this one has the best chance to happen this year.
I'll keep my fingers crossed for you then.
Knock on wood.
Now let's talk about one of your other famous
collaborations which is obviously Prince,
since this is after all the Schkopi Show 
the Web TV of Prince and the Minneapolis Sound fans.
I'm listening.
You can't even imagine how many questions I received on the forum
when it was announced you would participate in the show.
Really ?
We'll go back to this a bit later on.
But first, tell me how did you meet Prince ?
The first time I met him was at his home.
It was at 3121, the house he rented in Beverly Hills, Los Angeles.
It was a huge house with his symbol inlaid in the middle of the living room parquet.
When I got there there were very few people.
It was a Grammy party which was attended by Quincy Jones,
Erykah Badu, Common, Jamie Foxx,
Mariah Carey ...  many people were there, that said it was very intimate.
I was introduced to Prince, I shook his hand.
The Time was playing that night and one asked if I could jam with the band.
And his answer was, "We will listen to him, but another time".
Obviously, I wasn't expecting any other answer,
but it was still a little surprising to hear it.
That said, we spent a wonderful evening, but then we lost touch.
And one evening in November 2007, Stevie was playing
at Madison Square Garden, New York City,
and he asked me to do our little duet together.
So I went on stage after Tony Bennett.
Stevie did a duet with Tony Bennett on "For Once in My Life".
It was just with a piano, Tony and Stevie, and it was great.
Tony gave us the impression that the Madison Square Garden was a jazz club.
He has a voice which is so ... let's move on.
Once the audience was well warmed up by Tony and Stevie,
I heard the little bass line of "Boogie On Reggae Woman"
which began to rise on the keyboard,
and I thought then, here we go, it's my turn to play.
I went on stage and we did an absolutely extraordinary jam.
I believe from all the performances we did together that
was probably one of the best.
We ended up holding hands on stage
because Stevie had a little bit lost his balance
since he was playing and with hyperventilation it wasn't easy for him.
I kept him from falling in front of the stage and at the same time we were playing.
We found ourselves face to face and it was amazing.
The energy was really extraordinary at this moment,
it was great, everyone stood up.
I was very proud of me, I left the stage and went to get something to drink.
And then I came across Larry Graham, who wore his big coat and hat.
And I said to myself, My god, an apparition !
I asked him what he was doing here.
He said he came to have fun.
I asked him if he intended to play.
He said it wasn't at all his intention, he just came to listen to the concert.
And behind me I was hearing the audience was still screaming.
I thought to myself they were crazy.
I opened the curtain, everyone was screaming and looking at the stage,
everyone was having fun and had stood up.
I was wondering what was going on.
I looked onstage and saw my friend guitarist Errol Cooney on the side like this,
looking at something.
I thought, How come he's not playing guitar ?!
And I looked a little further and saw Prince on stage
playing "Superstition" with Stevie, and thought Ok, I get it now !
I was hoping to reconnect with him after the concert,
but he disappeared as fast as he appeared, as usual.
And it took another 6 months to wait before there was another party
which was held in his new home in Los Angeles and I was invited to attend.
That night we passed each other again.
When we were shaking hands I tried to remind him
of the Madison Square Garden concert, but he didn't recall it at all.
Around 10 minutes later, I was in a hallway talking to the
South Carolina singer Anthony Hamilton.
I explained to him how the harmonica works, as I showed you earlier.
And I heard someone saying,
"Oh, but you didn't play for Stevie but with Stevie.
I turned around and saw that Prince was watching the scene,
and for which it started to click.
Since that day, he started calling me and asked me to play in the studio
or at various events such as fundraisers, Grammy or Oscar after parties,
or even the European tour.
So I'll ask you questions from the forum members.
Let's go !
Did you ever suggest tracks or music directions to Prince,
if so, were your proposals selected ?
I did it once, and I won't do it again.
Oh ! Why ? What happened ?
He was clear on that, he's leading and I'm just following him.
Ok, so we stop talking about it.
Do you have the impression of belonging to the NPG band
or do you feel more like a recurring guest artist ?
I don't think I'm a member of the band.
I'm clearly a special and occasional guest.
The fact that I participated in most of his concerts over the past 2 years
doesn't make me an official member of the band.
On the contrary, I think he showed respect towards me.
In fact, when he invites me it's in order to spice up his music from time to time,
but it doesn't make me a member of the band.
Everyone knows it's a band which varies according to circumstances.
So maybe it isn't easy to get used to all the changes.
It is said there are 3 different line-ups for the NPG group.
Have you been asked to work with each of them or not at all ?
Yes, all of them except the last one,
because I haven't met the new bass player yet.
I don't know if you remember this, but when the Lotusflow3r album came out,
he wanted to use 3 groups for its promotion on The Tonight Show with Jay Leno.
NPG was the first one, the second one featured drummer Michael Bland
and bass player Sonny T. ...
He played with NPG on Wednesday and Friday,
and with Michael Bland and Sonny T. on Thursday night.
In theory, he should have played on Friday night with John Blackwell,
Rhonda Smith and Renato Nato, but for princely matters he changed his mind
at the last minute.
So, yes, I played with the 3 line-ups.
Do you have any preference between the 3 of them ?
They are all in a different vein.
The energy is truly different between the 3 groups.
I love Michael Bland's punch and Sonny T.'s virtuosity.
I like a lot the correlation between Josh and Cora.
It's absolutely extraordinary.
It's very hard to find a bass player and a drummer who live together
and who know each other very well musically,
it's amazing the correlation between the 2.
Between John Blackwell and Rhonda Smith, it's such a different spirit,
it works amazingly, but that's a total different world.
As for any preference, I'd say it depends on my mood.
Another question.
Do you think that being French was a plus in your collaboration with him,
knowing that he particularly likes France ?
He likes our culture.
He likes French fashion, food and architecture,
but when it comes to French music ...
When we went together to see a band play, he was rather surprised.
He was surprised by the fact that the band played a rather elaborated music,
and the audience was talking as if the music was only background sound.
He was a little disappointed by the fact that people paid no attention
to what was happening on stage, at least at this place.
I know he auditioned French musicians, but it hasn't been fruitful yet,
but you never can tell.
So, I don't know if my nationality really had an influence on our collaboration.
Ok, it was just a question from the forum members.
Sure.
I have my own idea on this, but why didn't you participate in the fall tour ?
What do you think of it ?
Maybe you and him had an argument ?
No, no, there was no tension.
I think he simply wanted something else.
Or maybe you had information that I didn't have.
That's it, in fact I have Prince's direct phone line, and he told me about it ...
That's it ! 777 - ...
I have to tell you something, I just love your shirt.
Thank you.
Its designer comes from Amsterdam, Netherlands.
I've been working with him for a while.
It's not because I'm a harmonicist that
I don't have the right to love fashion, right ?
You're so right !
So what else do we have in the list of questions?
In your opinion, can the harmonica replace the brass in Prince's music ?
It's a double-edged question.
The brass have a very specific color that convey a very different emotion
from what the harmonica can generate.
So, in my opinion, I think it's possible to replace them.
I don't think it has been done in Prince's music yet,
because it wasn't used for this purpose.
The harmonica was used in a very different way.
When he called me, it was because he really wanted to work on something
other than the brass.
What he had in mind wasn't really to replace them by the harmonica,
but to use it as an other color and function.
You may have read a lot of criticism regarding your participation
to Prince's summer tour.
Maybe some of them weren't very positive.
How did you feel about them ?
Today is the day to take the opportunity to get revenge !
Not at all.
On the one hand, I know most people come to Prince concerts to see Prince.
On the other hand, I can conceive the fact they like or not the harmonica,
but I think, in fact, it's my fault if I failed to convince and convert them
to the beauty of the instrument.
No, it's not your fault !
Now, I'm working on making up for it on my current project.
Give criticism if you really have something to say.
So, if they don't like the sound of the harmonica in Prince's music,
which I think was done maybe once or twice ...
I think I saw at the end of a DVD he brought in a harmonicist to jam,
but I don't think it was done on tour before.
Anyway, with him, everything is experimental.
Some things work, some others don't.
In my opinion, there were songs in which the harmonica was a nice addition.
Now there's one thing you need to know,
and I'm not saying this to defend myself,
but he never called me to rehearsals, so when I was invited to perform on stage,
I was discovering most of the songs while I was actually playing them.
A last word on this collaboration,
do you have any reproaches, things you loved, things which surprised you,
or made you angry?
No, I learned a lot of things during the time we collaborated together.
I learned to really focus on my project.
Now, I know what works for the harmonica and what doesn't,
thanks to the feedback I received for example on Prince fan forums.
I also know what works for the harmonica.
Now, I have a more clear direction on what I want to focus on.
This collaboration with him was extraordinary, I learned a lot musically.
I carefully observed him over the last 2 years, I took notes,
and now it's me do my thing.
So I consider I graduated from Prince high school, now it's time to go to college.
Thank you very much for participating and answering all our questions.
A final word for your French and international fans since this show is subtitled.
Thank you very much for giving me this opportunity to sit next to you, Pauline.
It was a real pleasure, thank you for your questions, thank you for your interest
and I hope we'll meet again very soon at concerts.
See you soon !